We all want to eat
the kinds of foods
that make us feel
better and live longer.
But there’s so much conflicting
information out there,
so many nutrition opinions.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s my job to give you
the information you need
to make the healthiest
choices possible.
Kidney disease ranks as the 9th
leading cause of death in the U.S.
So what foods should we eat
to keep our kidneys healthy?
Here’s our first story.
Chronic kidney disease is one
of the top ten leading causes
of premature death
in the United States,
and its incidence
is increasing.
Chronic kidney disease
affects more than 10 percent
of the adult population,
and each year,
more than 100,000 Americans
develop end-stage kidney disease
and have to go on dialysis.
What’s crazy is that a staggering
96 percent of individuals
with mild to moderate
decreases in kidney function
and about half
of individuals with severely
decreased kidney function
go undiagnosed.
Meaning the vast majority,
like 24 out of 25 people
with chronic kidney disease,
don’t even know
they have it.
What can we do to maintain
our kidney function?
Well, in a study that followed
more than a thousand older women
for a decade, those consuming
a diet that is richer
in plant-based protein had a slower
decline in kidney function,
extending support for the health
benefits of plant-rich diets
in the general population
to maintain kidney health.
Compared with protein
from plant sources,
animal protein has been associated
with an increased risk
of end-stage kidney disease
in several such studies.
We’re not exactly sure why.
Kidney damage from animal
protein could result
from the dietary acid load,
excess phosphorus,
or gut microbiome bad bacteria
and the resultant inflammation.
The dietary acid load in a Standard
American Diet is derived
mostly from animal sources
such as meats, eggs, and cheeses.
In contrast, by including
a higher proportion of foods
with natural alkali,
such as fruits and vegetables,
a strictly plant-based diet
is nearly acid neutral.
Even just eating plant-based
2 or 3 days a week
can significantly
bring down the acid load
delivered to the kidneys,
and eat plant-based full time,
and you can actually flip
over into alkaline territory.
Even just cutting out meat
can yield an alkaline load
compared to the acid
load in the nonvegetarians.
All this is important,
since dietary acid may promote
kidney injury and a progressive
decline in kidney function.
The intake of animal protein
can also cause an imbalance
in the composition of the gut
microbiome by producing
more ammonia and the rotten
egg gas hydrogen sulfide,
and have a proinflammatory
effect that may result
in reduced kidney function,
but it also may be
the animal fat.
In the Harvard Nurses Study,
higher intake of animal fat
was directly associated
with the loss of protein
in the urine,
which is a sign
of kidney damage,
and to protect against that,
they suggest diets lower
in animal protein,
animal fat, and cholesterol.
That may help
explain why vegetarians
have better kidney function
than nonvegetarians
matched for sex, age, size,
physical activity, alcohol, smoking, etc.
So effectively, even a meat eater
who is just as slim as a vegetarian,
just as healthy cholesterol,
blood pressure,
and blood sugar control-wise
still had inferior kidney function.
They think it might be
the higher dietary fiber intake
on more plant-based
diets contributing
to the protective effect
on kidney function,
again through
a microbiome mechanism.
Whereas the consumption
of animal protein may lead
to a proliferation
of meat-eating bugs,
which can result in a
leaky gut, uremic toxins,
and resulting inflammation,
oxidative stress,
and chronic kidney
disease progression.
That can be blocked, with
the decreased inflammation
and acid load thanks to the
eating of more fiber rich foods.
No wonder an egg-free
vegetarian dietary pattern
was associated with a 37 percent
decreased odds
of developing chronic
kidney disease.
But, what about plant-based diets
for not just the prevention
but the management
of chronic kidney disease?
Can comprehensive
lifestyle change alter
the course of chronic
kidney disease?
This was the case report
of someone diagnosed
with minimal
changes disease.
That’s when someone’s kidneys
start leaking protein,
even though there
are minimal changes seen
in biopsies under
the microscope.
You give people steroids,
and in a few months,
you can knock it down,
but a significant fraction
may fail to respond
to the steroid therapy.
He was diagnosed
18 years prior,
but only by replacing animal
protein with plant-based protein
was he able
to put his chronic
kidney disease
into remission.
At age 44, he suddenly developed
swelling that crept up
throughout his body since
he was losing so much protein.
He was weak, unable
to concentrate, and lethargic.
Diagnosed with
minimal change disease
and treated with a water pill
and four different blood
pressure lowering agents.
Because of unresponsiveness
to high-dose steroids,
a powerful immunosuppressant
was added;
yet, severe protein
loss continued
and his hypertension and
kidney function worsened
until...he started eating
plant-based,
started exercising,
lost 60 pounds,
and his kidney disease
went away and stayed away.
Let’s hear it
in his own words.
“I appreciate the recommendations
my doctor gave me
about making
dietary modifications:
‘replace your protein intake
with plant-based protein.’
This one change has had
a monumental impact on my life.
I have gained back a quality of life
that I thought was gone forever.
My benchmark for normal
has been my ability to keep up
with my professional work demands
and still be able to exercise.
For the last 7 months, I now swim
over three miles every other day:
a distance that surpasses
my pre–kidney disease life.
I perceived I lived a healthy
lifestyle before kidney disease;
today, I live a healthier,
happier lifestyle,
and I have my kidneys
to thank for it.
In our next story,
we look at the significant dietary risk
factors for declining kidney function.
Kidney failure may be both prevented
and treated with a plant-based diet,
and no wonder; kidneys are
highly vascular organs.
Harvard researchers found three
significant dietary risk factors
for declining kidney function: animal
protein, animal fat, and cholesterol.
Animal fat can alter the actual structure
of our kidneys, based on studies like this,
showing plugs of fat literally clogging up
the works in autopsied human kidneys.
And the animal protein can
have a profound effect
on normal kidney function,
inducing what's called hyperfiltration,
increasing the workload of
the kidney; but not plant protein.
Eat a meal of tuna fish and you can see
the increased pressure on the kidneys
go up within 1, 2, 3 hours after the meal,
in both nondiabetics and diabetics.
So we're not talking adverse
effects decades down the road,
but literally within hours
of it going into our mouth.
Now, if instead of having a tuna
salad sandwich, though,
you had a tofu salad sandwich,
with the exact same amount
of protein, what happens?
No effect.
Dealing with plant protein
is no problem.
Why does animal protein cause the
overload reaction, but not plant protein?
It appears to be due to
the inflammation triggered
by the consumption
of animal products.
How do we know that?
Because, if you give a powerful,
anti-inflammatory drug
along with that tuna fish, you
can abolish the hyperfiltration,
protein leakage response
to meat ingestion.
Then, there's the acid load.
Animal foods—meat, eggs, and dairy—
induce the formation of acid
within the kidneys, which
may lead to tubular toxicity,
damage to the tiny, delicate,
urine-making tubes in the kidney.
Animal foods tend to be acid forming—
especially fish, which is the worst—
then pork and poultry,
whereas plant foods tend
to be relatively neutral,
or actually alkaline, base-forming
to counteract the acid.
So the key to halting the progression
of chronic kidney disease
might be in the produce market,
rather than the pharmacy.
Finally today,
I share a touching story of the
power of plant-based eating
for chronic kidney failure.
Is it possible to ameliorate
chronic kidney disease
using a whole food,
plant-based diet?
In my last video
on kidney disease,
I talked about how randomizing
people to cut just around
10 grams of protein from their
daily diet could cut their risk
of dialysis and death
by a whopping 77%.
That was cutting protein
across the board.
But while animal-based
protein ingestion —
meat, dairy, and egg white
promotes an acidic environment
in the kidneys, inflammation, and
stresses the kidneys to what's
called hyperfiltration mode,
plant-based protein can be
alkaline-producing and
anti-inflammatory and contain
kidney-protective properties.
So, what if you have kidney patients
eat a plant-dominant low-protein diet,
abbreviated adorably as PLADO,
I guess for plant-dominant.
If you fashion up a plant-based diet
index score where you get points
for healthy plant foods
and get points deducted
for eating animal foods,
those with serious kidney disease
with higher scores were found
to have lower systemic inflammation.
But does that actually translate
into living a longer life?
Apparently so.
Even a 10% increase in the
proportion of plant-based protein
was associated with a significant
reduction in all-cause mortality.
Even just eating more servings of
fruits and vegetables, like two a day
compared to two a week,
is linked to living longer.
Without fully functioning kidneys,
there are concerns about
phosphorus and potassium overload,
though, on a plant-based diet.
But the phosphorus in plant-based
foods is not as much of a problem
as the phosphorus additives
in processed and animal foods.
And the risk of potassium overload
from plant-based diets appears
overstated and not supported
by the evidence.
But you don't know about
ameliorating chronic kidney disease
using a whole food, plant-based
diet until you put it to the test.
Here's a case report of a 69-year-old
man with type 2 diabetes,
high blood pressure, and
stage 3 chronic kidney disease,
resulting in elevated phosphorus
and potassium in the blood,
Interested in changing his diet
to improve his medical condition.
That's my kind of patient!
He was on 12 different medications,
eating a diet that may actually be
slightly better than
the average American:
some whole grains and beans,
but then his doctor advised to try
eating whole food, plant-based.
So, oatmeal with fruit and flax,
beans and greens,
whole wheat spaghetti and
veggies, fruit as snacks.
Counselled to eat as much as he
wanted from whole healthy foods;
no carb counting, no calorie counting,
no portion size restriction —
improving the quality of food rather
than restricting the quantity of food.
He adopted the whole food,
plant-based diet, packed with carbs,
yet rapidly reduced his insulin
requirements by more than 50%,
and subsequently saw
improvements in weight,
blood pressure,
and cholesterol.
Because eating healthy
can have such a rapid effect
on improving your body's
insulin sensitivity,
immediate adjustments
in insulin dosing were made.
Within four days, his insulin dose
was able to be reduced
from roughly 210 units of insulin
a day down to 70 units daily,
and an oral blood-sugar lowering
medication had to be stopped
due to rapidly improving blood sugar.
He also was able to stop his
carvedilol, the hydrochlorothiazide,
amlodipine, sitagliptin
within the first two months
due to improving blood pressure
and blood sugars.
His insulin dose was
steadily titrated downward.
His pravastatin dose was cut in half,
and he lost about 50 pounds.
Okay, so what happened
to his stage 3 kidney failure?
He was no longer in
stage 3 kidney failure!
He experienced an increase
in estimated GFR of 73%,
suggesting that the improvement
in estimated kidney function
was greater than what would be
expected from weight loss alone.
For example, lose about 60 pounds
from bariatric surgery,
and you only get
about a 12 to 15% boost.
Bottom line: for individuals
with chronic kidney disease,
especially those with obesity,
hypertension, or diabetes,
a strict, all-you-care-to-eat
whole food, plant-based diet
may confer significant benefit.
I mean, apart from the
kidney-specific outcomes,
overall mortality is significantly
lower among kidney patients
who eat more plants.
And that's critical because most
kidney patients don't even make it
to dialysis because they die first,
most often from
cardiovascular disease.
Let's hear from the patient.
"At the outset, it seemed like
this was going to be a difficult
and restrictive way to eat,
but I began feeling different
almost immediately
and we had to decrease
my insulin after ONE day.
It seemed like almost overnight I had
more energy than I'd had in years.
Weight I'd been trying to lose for
a decade began dropping off.
As the weight came off, I felt lighter,
and more able to move my body again.
This lifestyle change has been
the greatest gift I've ever received.
I am off most of my medications,
I've lost over 70 pounds,
and I've regained control
over my health.
I feel empowered
by this lifestyle change,
and I finally feel like I'm
in charge of my health,
not just an unlucky victim shuffling
from one specialist to the next.
My only regret was that
I didn't know about this sooner."
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.